Finding Aid for the James, Meadows & Howard Records 1893-1974 (bulk 1951-1971)
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
James, Meadows & Howard Records
1893 - 1974
1951 - 1971
Mss. C74-2
James, Meadows & Howard
135 boxes (67.5 linear feet)
The records of the architectural firm of James, Meadows & Howard represents the accumulated archives of a firm dating back ninety years.
The Buffalo History Museum 1 Museum Court Buffalo, NY 14216 Phone: 716-873-9644 ext. 306 Fax: 716-873-8754 Email: library@buffalohistory.org URI: http://www.buffalohistory.org
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
James, Meadows & Howard Records, 1893-1974 (bulk 1951-1971), are open for research.
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
James, Meadows & Howard; gift; 1973/11/13; 74-3
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
Two ledgers from this collection were digitized by the LIS 567 Digital Libraries class of the University at Buffalo's Department of Library and Information Studies. The collection is located at:
http://www.bechs.org/Greenstone/green/index.php
Historical Note
Buffalo architectural firm which originally began as Green & Wicks in 1884. It became Edward B. Green & Son in 1917 and, upon the death of the son in 1933, Edward B. Green. R. Maxwell James joined the firm in 1930 as a designer and became a partner in Green & James in 1936. Rufus W. Meadows, who joined as a designer in 1936, became a partner in Green, James & Meadows in 1945. When Mr. Green died in 1950, the partners continued under the name James & Meadows. Lewis E. Howard, Jr., a former associate, rejoined Green, James & Meadows in 1946. In 1953 he became a partner in James, Meadows & Howard. The firm's designs included the Federal Reserve Bank on South Elmwood Avenue, and buildings in the Buffalo General Hospital and Children's Hospital complexes, Erie County Medical Center, and at the University of Buffalo. Mr. Howard died in 1956. The firm was dissolved in 1974.
Chronology
1884 Green & Wicks founded.
1917 Edw. B. Green & Son.
1933 Edw. B. Green - Son died.
1936 Green & James.
1945 Green, James & Meadows.
1950 James & Meadows - Green died.
1952 James, Meadows & Howard.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the architectural firm of James, Meadows & Howard represents the accumulated archives of a firm dating back ninety years. The records include log books, construction specification books, bids, contracts, plans and blueprints, correspondence, invoices, site photographs and other records of an architectural firm of local importance commissioned to design a wide variety of structures, including many hospitals, churches, banks and other commercial buildings.
Specifications for Falconwood Club, Buffalo Historical Society Building, Clifton Park Memorial, Crippled Children's Home, and Albright Art Gallery Transferred from Iconography section, 1975.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in four series:
I. Log Books
II. Construction Specifications
III. Job Files
IV. Miscellaneous Photographs, Concrete Site Reports, Cost Books and Contracts.
The archival practice of maintaining the original arrangement of the firm's records has been carefully observed here. Alphabetical arrangement within series.
Container List
- Log Books, 1951-1968, I.
  - American Radiator Standard Sanitary Corporation May 7, 1962; Aug. 2, 1962 (Box 1, Volume 1)
  - Buffalo General Hospital, Nurses' Residence May 24, 1967; Feb. 27, 1968 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Broadway Market, Aug. 23, 1954 (Box 1, Volume 3)
  - Buffalo Medical Center, May 1951; June-Aug. 1952 (Box 1, Volume 4)
  - University Medical Building, May 1, 1951 (Box 1, Volume 5)
  - University of Buffalo, Sherman Hall, Oct. 24, 1957; Dormitories, 1952-1959 (Box 1, Volume 6)
- Construction Specifications, 1893-1971, II.
  - Albright, Charlotte, residence, Apr. 20, 1962 (Box 2)
  - American Radiator and Standard Sanitary Corp., Mar.-Nov. 1962 (Box 2)
  - Bank of Buffalo (Court and Pearl Streets), Aug. 24, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Bank of Buffalo (French and Borden Roads), May 28, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Bank of Buffalo (Stuyvesant Plaza), May 6, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Boys' Club of Niagara Frontier, May 31, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Broadway Market, Mar. 15, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Broadway Market (continued), 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - Brooks Memorial Hospital, Dunkirk, N.Y., Dec. 6, 1961 (Box 3)
  - Buffalo Club, June 20, 1960 (Box 3)
  - Buffalo Columbus Hospital, East Bldg. 2nd floor, Jan. 19, 1970 (Box 3)
  - Buffalo Columbus Hospital (continued), 1970 (Box 4)
  - Buffalo General Hospital, Nurses' Residence, Feb. 13, 1967 (Box 4)
  - Buffalo General Hospital, Multi-Laboratory Bldg, June 5, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Buffalo General Hospital, South Wing, Dec. 12, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Buffalo Gravel Corporation, June 25, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Buffalo Historical Society, 1926, 1950 (Box 4)
  - Buffalo Medical Foundation, May 1960 (Box 5)
  - Buffalo Medical Foundation, Medical Office Building, Aug. 9, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Buffalo Savings Bank (Main and Genesee Streets) 1965 (Box 6)
  - Buffalo Savings Bank (Amherst office), 1970 (Box 7)
  - Children's Hospital, Nov. 17, 1961 (Box 7)
  - Church of the Good Shepherd, May 6, 1960 (Box 7)
  - Columbus-McKinnon Corporation, Sept. 24, 1964 (Box 7)
  - Deaconess Hospital, Nov. 26, 1958 (Box 7)
  - Deaconess Hospital (continued), 1960, 1963, 1966 (Box 8)
  - Episcopal Church Home, July 16, 1956 (Box 8)
  - Erie County Hall, Jan. 1, 1937 (Box 8)
  - Erie County Jail, Jan. 1, 1937; Oct. 25, 1954 (Box 8)
  - Erie County Jail (continued), 1967-1968 (Box 9)
  - Erie County Savings Bank, 1965, 1967 (Box 9)
  - Falconwood Club, Boat House, May 5, 1893 (Box 9)
  - Family Service Society, 1951, 1962 (Box 10)
  - Federal Reserve Bank of New York, 1955-1956 (Box 10)
  - Flat Building for Henry Schaefer's Sons, 1898 (Box 10)
  - Foster-Milburn Company, Apr. 19, 1963 (Box 10)
  - Frontier Linen Supply, Aug. 12, 1966 (Box 10)
  - Garret Club, Mar. 30, 1966 (Box 11)
  - William Hengerer Company, May 7, 1956 (Box 11)
  - Kissing Bridge Ski Corporation, Aug. 8, 1960 (Box 11)
  - Legislative Building (Albany South Mall), June 29, 1966 (Box 11)
  - Liberty National Bank, Feb. 20, 1964 (Box 12)
  - Lincoln Wholesale Building, 1960 (Box 12)
  - Lockport Memorial Hospital, Dec. 13, 1960; 1970 (Box 12)
  - Manufacturer's and Trader's Trust Co., Mar. 26, 1965 (Box 12)
  - Marine Trust Co., 1956-1967 (Box 13)
  - Merchants Mutual Insurance Co., 1964 (Box 13)
  - E.J. Meyer Memorial Hospital, 1961-1963 (Box 14)
  - Municipal Building, 1936; 1938 (Box 14)
  - Municipal Auditorium (continued), 1939 (Box 15)
  - Niagara Frontier Rehabilitation Center, 1964 (Box 15)
  - Niagara Mohawk, 1961; 1966-1967 (Box 16)
  - Parking garages, 1953-1955 (Box 16)
  - St. Joseph Intercommunity Hospital, 1958; 1965; 1968-1969 (Box 17)
  - St. Mark's Church, 1940-1941: 1953; 1961 (Box 18)
  - St. Stephen Serbian Orthodox Church,, June 2, 1958 (Box 18)
  - Terminal Building, Aug. 7, 1967 (Box 18)
  - Trinity Episcopal Church, Apr. 23, 1958 (Box 18)
  - United States Post Office, June-Sept. 1961 (Box 18)
  - University of Buffalo (Dormitory Authority), Jan. 1962 (Box 19)
  - University of Buffalo, Residence Hall no. 6, 1959 (Box 19)
  - University of Buffalo, Dormitory no. 7, 1962-1963 (Box 19)
  - Albright Art Gallery, June 3, 1957 (Box 19A)
  - Clifton Park Memorial, March 11, 1921 (Box 19A)
  - Crippled Children's Home, Jan.-June 1938 (Box 19A)
  - Erie County Stadium, 1972 (Box 19A)
- Job Files, circa 1931-1971, III.
  - Albright, Charlotte residence, 1962 (Box 20)
  - Architect's Redevelopment Cooperative, 1963 (Box 20)
  - American Radiator and Standard Sanitary Corporation, 1961-1963 (Box 20)
  - American-Standard (continued) (Box 21)
  - Bank of Buffalo, 1960-1966 (Box 22)
  - Boy's Club of Buffalo, 1965 (Box 23)
  - Broadway Market 1958-1965 (Box 23)
  - Brooks Memorial Hospital (Dunkirk, N.Y.), 1961-1969 (Box 24)
  - Brooks Memorial Hospital (continued), 1961-1969 (Box 24A)
  - Buffalo Club, circa 1958 (Box 24A)
  - Buffalo General Hospital, circa 1958-1969 (Box 24A-30A)
  - Buffalo Gravel Corporation, circa 1964 (Box 31A)
  - Buffalo Historical Society, circa 1966 (Box 31)
  - Buffalo Medical Group Building, circa 1968-1970 (Box 31)
  - Buffalo Medical Group (continued) (Box 31A)
  - Buffalo Medical Group (continued) (Box 32)
  - Buffalo Savings Bank (Box 33-39)
  - Children's Hospital, circa 1954-1968 (Box 39A-45)
  - Civil Defense (Box 46)
  - Columbus Hospital, circa 1963-1968 (Box 47-50)
  - Dayton Museum, circa 1931 (Box 51)
  - Deaconess Hospital, circa 1957-1967 (Box 51-60)
  - Degraff Memorial Hospital, circa 1951 (Box 60)
  - Delaware Court Building Doctor's Hospital, circa 1968 (Box 60)
  - Episcopal Church Home, circa 1965 (Box 61)
  - Erie County Savings Bank, circa 1966-1969 (Box 61-62)
  - Erie County Jail, circa 1955-1970 (Box 62-65)
  - Family Service Society Building, circa 1962 (Box 66)
  - First Federal Savings and Loan Association, circa 1952 (Box 66)
  - Federal Reserve Bank, circa 1953-1960 (Box 66-75)
  - First Methodist Church (Bradford, PA), circa 1924-1967 (Box 76)
  - The William Hengerer Company, circa 1955-1957 (Box 77-79)
  - Hospitals and Asylums (Box 80)
  - Iroquois Division (International Breweries, Inc.), circa 1956 (Box 80)
  - Junior High School # 91, circa 1956-1960 (Box 80)
  - Kissing Bridge Ski Corporation, circa 1960 (Box 80)
  - Liberty Bank (Orchard Park), circa 1964 (Box 81)
  - Lockport Hospital circa 1962-1967 (Box 82-83)
  - Marine Trust Company, circa 1954-1967 (Box 84-90)
  - Mayfair lane (photographs), 1930 (Box 91)
  - Medical Office Building (Buffalo Medical Group), circa 1969 (Box 91)
  - Memorial Tablets (Box 91)
  - Merchants Mutual, circa 1963-1965 (Box 91-95)
  - E.J. Meyer Memorial Hospital, circa 1957-1964 (Box 96)
  - Niagara Frontier Rehabilitation Center, circa 1964-1967 (Box 97)
  - Niagara Square Office Building, circa 1967 (Box 97)
  - Orchard Heights Clubhouse, circa 1960 (Box 97)
  - Post Office, circa 1960-1964 (Box 98-104)
  - St. James Evangelical Lutheran Church, circa 1956 (Box 105)
  - St. Mark's Church, circa 1961 (Box 105)
  - St. Paul's Lutheran Church (Box 105)
  - Trinity Church Home (Box 105)
  - St. Joseph Intercommunity Hospital, circa 1965-1971 (Box 106-110)
  - Legislative Office Building (Albany, N.Y.), circa 1963 (Box 111)
  - University of Buffalo: Capen Hall, circa 1958 (Box 112)
  - University of Buffalo: Clark Gymnasium addition, circa 1958 (Box 112)
  - University of Buffalo: Dormitory Authority of NYS (Box 112)
  - University of Buffalo: Norton Hall (Box 112)
  - University of Buffalo: Physics Building (Box 113)
  - University of Buffalo: Engineering Building (Box 113)
  - University of Buffalo: School of Dentistry addition (Box 113)
  - University of Buffalo: Warehouse Building (Box 113)
  - University of Buffalo: Residence Hall #4 (Box 114-115)
  - University of Buffalo: Residence Hall #6 (Box 116-118)
  - University of Buffalo: Residence Hall #7 (Box 119-122)
  - Veterans' Hospital, circa 1952 (Box 123)
  - W.C.A. Hospital, circa 1961 (Box 123)
  - Woman's Christian Association, circa 1961 (Box 123)
- Miscellaneous, IV.
  - Miscellaneous progress photographs, 1909-1970 (Box 124)
  - Concrete Site Reports (Box 125-125A)
  - Cost books, 1909-1921 (Box 126)
  - Contracts, 1957-1969 (Box 126)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (JM & H staff, etc.) (Box 126)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
James & Meadows; Green & Wicks; Edward B. Green & Son; Green & James; Buffalo History Museum
Subject Terms
Architecture--New York (State); Hospitals--New York (State)--Planning
Genre Terms
Photographs; Architectural drawings (visual works); Building plans